<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The assurance of the faithfull, or, The glorious estate of the saints in heaven described and the certainty of their future happiness manifested by reason and Scripture / by M.D.</title>
            <author>D'Assigny, Marius, 1643-1717.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1670</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 82 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A37048</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D282</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24872</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08630211</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08630211</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41499</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A37048)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41499)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1255:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The assurance of the faithfull, or, The glorious estate of the saints in heaven described and the certainty of their future happiness manifested by reason and Scripture / by M.D.</title>
                  <author>D'Assigny, Marius, 1643-1717.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.R. for Edward Man,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1670.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Epistle dedicatory" signed: M. D'Assigny.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Heaven.</term>
               <term>Future life.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41499:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41499:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The ASSURANCE OF THE FAITHFULL: OR, The Glorious Eſtate Of the Saints in Heaven, <hi>DESCRIBED:</hi> And the certainty of their future Happineſs mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted by REASON and Scripture. By <hi>M. D.</hi> Batchelor of Divinity.</p>
            <q>Parva non ſunt contemnenda fine quibus magna conſtare non poſſunt. <bibl>
                  <hi>Seneca.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Ratio fide praecedente plurimum valet. <bibl>
                  <hi>Aug. Epiſt. 222.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Ratio ſubſequatur fidem ut intelligat fidelis quid credat. <bibl>
                  <hi>Ambroſ. de fide contra Arrianos.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed by <hi>J. R.</hi> for <hi>Edward Man,</hi> at the Sign of the Swan in the <hi>Strand,</hi> near <hi>York-houſe.</hi> 1670.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:41499:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41499:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honorable Lady <hi>ELIZABETH,</hi> Counteſs Dowager of <hi>Northumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Was afraid to venture theſe Meditations from the Pulpit to the Preſs, through a mixed multitude a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone without a Protection; for although they have had the happineſs to be well received in a famous Audience, eſpecially from the Perſons of Quality who have perſwaded me to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them to appear in publick:
<pb facs="tcp:41499:3"/>I knew not but that they might meet with ſome moroſe and ill-natur'd <hi>Zoilus,</hi> whoſe common practice is to beſpatter the beſt approved Writings of our age; but ſince your Honour favours them with your acceptance, I have been delivered from all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion: I fear no more the miſtakes of the ignorant, and the malice of our ſenſual Wits, becauſe I am certain that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one will have ſome eſteem and reſpect for thoſe Labours, that are honoured with the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation and Allowance of a perſon of that ſingular Wiſdom and Piety; And not onely my private benefit hath obliged me to this Dedication, but alſo that
<pb facs="tcp:41499:3"/>of my Friends unto whom I do not onely diſcover the unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Excellencies of Heaven, but beſides I reveal unto them the means of attaining unto that bleſſed End. The former they shall find in the Sermon, and the latter they may meet with in the Preface, in your Honour, and in your moſt Exemplary life; A life that makes you appear an Ornament amongſt our English Nobility, and eſpecially to the moſt noble Families that are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated unto your Honour,
<note n="*" place="margin">The moſt noble Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of the <hi>Howards.</hi>
               </note> One of them God hath bleſt with a numerous increaſe of Perſons of the greateſt worth: A Life wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of our admiration, in that it shews us Piety, Vertue, Wiſdom,
<pb facs="tcp:41499:4"/>Goodneſs, and Honour, as ſo many Celeſtial Lights shining together in the ſame Sphere; A Miracle in Grace as well as Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture! A Bleſſing it is to our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in this unhappy Age, that we have ſome ſuch Noble Souls, that ſeem to be Angels Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, ſent amongſt us by the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Appointment on purpoſe to maintain the Honour of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion againſt the encroachings of Schiſm and Profaneſs. It is unto ſuch Heavenly Spirits, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> that Chriſt promiſeth a Crown of Life; not onely to encourage them in a faithful management of his, and their Spiritual concerns, but alſo to oblige them to a total Reſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:41499:4"/>of themſelves and intereſts to the diſpoſition of his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and to enable them to bear worldly misfortunes, and preſent affliction with leſs pain. I do therefore offer the deſcription of that extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry felicity unto your Honour, as a ſeaſonable meditation, where your Piety, <hi>Madam,</hi> may meet with Antidotes able to preſerve your Noble Mind from the ſence of all evil events: And as the Original shall one day be worthy your acceptance, be pleaſed now to look favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably upon this Repreſentation, which will afford your Honour a ſight of thoſe precious Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els that enrich the Heavenly
<pb facs="tcp:41499:5"/>Crown. Here is alſo the Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that Faith and Reaſon do give of that Glorious Eſtate un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Faithful: God preſerve your Honour in much health and proſperity, with all your Noble Relations; It is the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty deſire, and shall always be the Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours moſt Faithful and devoted Servant <hi>M. D'Aſſigny.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41499:5"/>
            <head>The Aſſurance of the Faithful: <hi>OR,</hi> Heavens Glory made manifeſt. In a Sermon upon theſe words of the 2d Chapter of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> the latter part of the 10th verſe.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>I will give thee a Crown of life.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen a Glorious Victory is aſſured, what faint-hearted Souldier will ſhun the encounter? When the price of a Race is ineſtimable, who will not run to obtain it? or when Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards are promiſed, whoſe acquiſition will procure unto us immortal ſatisfactions, who will delay the performance of the Task? who will not be encouraged to labour after the purchaſe? Such is the nature of the Victory over our Spiritual enemies of the price of Virtues race, and of thoſe Coeleſtial Rewards that invite as to the accompliſhment of our great Task of obedience to the ſupreme Authority. They are ſuch as becomes an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite bounty to beſtow: ſuch as have required both an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite power to create, and blood of an infinite value to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem. They are ſuch as are carefully laid up in thoſe hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly manſions where all things are ſuitable unto that Majeſty, that diſcovers it ſelf there inveſted with an incomprehenſible Glory. It ſeems Chriſt the eternal Son of God, who is very well acquainted with theſe ſupernatural Excellencies, had no mean eſteem of their value and power, ſeeing that he judges them ſufficient to recompenſe, and able to encourage the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:41499:6"/>in violent perſecutions. He judges them worth their labours and ſufferings. Therefore in his letters to his ſeven beloved Churches of <hi>Aſia</hi> minor, that were threatned with the furious aſſaults of the enemies of the truth, he annexes to his reproofs and exhortations a bleſſed declaration of the greatneſs of Heavens glory, as the aſſured Reward of their faithfulneſs, that theſe future hopes might fill them with the contempt of the preſent difficulties, raiſe their ſpirits in the midſt of temporal afflictions with the joyful expectation of that ineſtimable happineſs, and oblige them to encounter all oppoſition with an inflexible courage and patience. Theſe advantages promiſed to their perſeverance are many and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, yet he ſummes them up in ſuch different Titles as had ſome relation either to the preſent eſtate of thoſe Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, or unto thoſe things that were moſt in eſteem in thoſe Regions where they were ſituated. Unto the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> he preſents them under the notion of the fruits of the Tree of Life, either becauſe the ſoils did yield moſt excellent fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trees, and eſpecially one called by the Naturaliſts <hi>Arbor vitae,</hi> whoſe fruit is of an extraordinary vertue, or becauſe that Church was in a decaying condition: Chriſt promiſeth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Heaven as a Soveraign Remedy to all the evils that did torment them, borrowing an expreſſion from that wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Tree that was appointed to preſerve man in the eſtate of Innocency in his perfection from all thoſe weakneſſes. Unto them of <hi>Pergamus</hi> Chriſt calls the rewards of Heaven, a white Stone, becauſe that City being a place of Judicature, and the Reſidence of a Proconſul, they were acquainted with the manner of abſolving the accuſed, which was by caſting a white ſtone into a Pot; Chriſt thereby intimating the joyes of the Saints in Heaven much like unto thoſe of a Criminal, when he received from his Judge a white ſtone of abſolution inſtead of a black one of condemnation which he had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved. Thus unto the Church of <hi>Smyrna</hi> for other reaſons which we ſhall examine, he calls the glories of Heaven, a Grown of life. This laſt name ſignifies more than appears
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:41499:6"/>at the firſt aſpect: you may perceive the ſuperficial part of the bleſſedneſs and glories of Heaven. It will be worth your while to know their extraordinary value, that they may be alſo unto you an encouragement to Duty. Both our Saviours goodneſs that holds them out unto us, and offers them to our contemplation here, and to our fruition hereafter; and their own excellencies do invite us to enquire into them, that we may know what we have to expect from Gods liberality, and that accordingly we may order our endeavours. To the end you may meet with ſatisfaction in this inquiſition, we ſhall labour to repreſent unto you the glorious eſtate of the Elect in Heaven with the ſame Colours that it appears in my Text: And firſt we ſhall ſee what is this Crown of life, and wherefore it is ſo called. Secondly, the Aſſurance that the Text gives of this Eſtate unto the faithful, which we ſhall prove as well by Reaſon, as the Authority of Scripture. But before we proceed, we ſhall make ſome few obſervations.</p>
            <p>It were no ordinary Preſumption to engage in a perfect de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of this Crown of Life; when our weak capacities that are confined by our ſenſes to this lower ſphere, cannot at preſent aſcend to a full contemplation of coeleſtial bodies that enrich the Firmament, much leſs can we attain unto a clear apprehenſion of higher and more divine objects. Their ſuperlative excellency frees them from the profanation and acquaintance of Judgements that converſe onely amongſt the meaneſt beings. An ancient Crecian petitioned the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then gods, that he might be admitted to behold the Sun at a near diſtance.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fide non cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitur, ſpe non attingitur, charitate non apprehendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur; acquiri potest, estima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri non poteſt vita eterna.</hi> Szeged.</note> It would be in vain to entertain the ſame curioſity in this caſe, and to deſire to come now to a perfect knowledge of this ſupernatural condition, becauſe whiles ignorance and prejudice do poſſeſs our Underſtandings, and vanity our Wills, we are neither worthy nor capable to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ſuch ſublime notions. St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s modeſty therefore becomes us who are not favoured with unſpeakable Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; He dares not venture to deſcribe thoſe myſteries that were reſerved for his experience and ſenſe: <hi>That eye hath not
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41499:7"/>ſeen, ear hath not heard, and that are not entered into the heart of man.</hi> Yet we muſt not ſo far miſtake the Apoſtles Practice, and our own Duty, as to make his diſcretion the cauſe of our negligence, and to forbid all meditations of Heaven as unlawful, becauſe he recommends unto us ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety in our inquiries, and as impoſſible becauſe of its di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from our climate. This reſpectful ignorance is unſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable in this unbelieving age: a friend unto Senſuality and Atheiſme, and an enemy of thoſe comforts which ſuch conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations do yield to ſweeten the bitterneſs of our earthly ſorrows. Beſides, this were to condemn Chriſts intention, and to fruſtrate his deſign. Wherefore doth he offer them to the contemplation of his Churches, and propoſes them as the aſſured recompenſe of the labours of the faithful? Wherefore do the ſacred Writers mention unto us ſo often the advantages of the other life? but that we ſhould know, admire, and expect theſe Riches of Gods goodneſs; that we ſhould endeavour to attain unto them, and that the hopes of immortal Bliſs might make us bear temporal misfortunes, and the preſent unhappineſs of the world with leſs repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy.
<note place="margin">Heb. 12.2.</note> It is the deſign of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Exhortation, <hi>Let us run,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the race that is ſet before us, looking unto Jeſus the author and finiſher of our faith: who for the joy that was ſet before him endured the Croſs, deſpiſing the ſhame, and is ſet down at the right hand of the throne of God.</hi> That we may follow this glorious example of our Saviour, and arrive at laſt at the ſame felicities, they are ſhewed unto us afar off: the diſtance as of all other objects that preſent themſelves to our ſenſes, leſſens their greatneſs, and our preſent eſteem of their worth; and thoſe things that interpoſe between them and us, occaſions this ingenuous Confeſſion of the Apoſtle, <hi>Now we ſee through a glaſs darkly, we know in part, and we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs in part.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This imperfection proceeds partly from the weakneſs of Man's judgement, and partly from the ſublimity and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of the poſſeſſions of Heaven; which are repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41499:7"/>unto us by thoſe earthly things that have but a faint reſemblance with their qualities and nature. Beſides theſe advantages of the life to come are as many as glorious, and therefore it is impoſſible to find a perfect Relation, a perfect Image of the ſeveral parcels of Heavens Glory in any one excellency of the World. When they ſhould meet all in one Center, and joyn their diſperſed beams and powers, they would not be able to repreſent one of the Rayes of eternal felicity; and when ſuch a ſignificant word might be invented that could comprehend all the comforts, the bleſſedneſs, and all the pomp of the World; it would not be ſufficient to ſhew us the leaſt part of the happineſs of this life. Divers names are therefore borrowed from theſe earthly vanities to ſhadow thoſe realities, becauſe of ſome weak relation that they have with this bleſſed condition: Its Joyes are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by a Marriage, its Glory by the Sun and Stars, its In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependency and Power by a Royalty, our Holineſs by the Prieſthood, our abode by a City fenced with Rubies and Diamonds, paved with Chryſtal and Saphyrs, and enriched with Gold and the moſt precious Stones. Amongſt the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Deſcriptions employed to give us a ſight of Heavenly Bliſs, I find none of ſo large an extent, and of ſuch an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Comprehenſion as that in my text, <hi>I will give thee a Crown of life.</hi> In which words the ſweetneſs and pleaſures of that eſtate, the Glory, the Splendor, the Majeſty, and pomp of it do jointly appear together; for it is a life, a true life, full of all innocent delights that will render it both real and pleaſant, and that will free us from all Syncopes that do now frequently interrupt our life. Beſides it ſhall be a Crown of life, the glories will be anſwerable to the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of it: it ſhall be a living Crown,
<note place="margin">Hebraiſme.</note> as ſome will have the words rendted: Thoſe excellent enjoyments that we ſhall poſſeſs, and that ſupream degree of honour unto which we ſhall be promoted ſignified by this Crown, ſhall continue with us for all eternity in the ſame unchangeable condition, therefore St.
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.4.</note> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> calls it a Crown of Glory that <hi>fadeth not
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41499:8"/>away.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.25. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> And St. <hi>Paul</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The Hebrew word uſed in ſuch like occaſions, to expreſs the ſublimeſt felicity of Chriſt, and of his Saints, ſignifies as well the plenty as the eternity of their advantages.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>He encompaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed about.</hi> Pſal. 21.3.</note> We may hereby underſtand that this Crown of life ſhall intitle them to innumerable and immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal ſatisfactions: it ſhall therefore be a true life. How wrongfully do we abuſe this pleaſant Title in beſtowing it upon the preſent unworthy ſubſiſtency of the ſoul and body? O miſerable eſtate! how vainly do we flatter our beings with this gratefull conceit? Can that ever be a life, that drags us continually to our Grave, that cauſeth us to die as ſoon as we begin to breathe, and that is joyned unto death by the inward Principles of our exiſtence? Can that be a life that carries death in its boſome, that makes us ſenſible of a thouſand deaths before we breathe forth the laſt gaſp, and that is interrupted by ſleep, idleneſs, and ſickneſs, (as by ſo many deaths) which deprive us of the benefits of life, by which it is to be eſteemed rather than by the continuance of the ſoul with the body, at leaſt in the judgement of a wiſe Moraliſt, who hearing of a wicked man that was lately ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired in a very old age; <hi>Diu fuit,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>ſed non diu vixit.</hi> At this rate how unworthy is our preſent ſubſiſtence of the pleaſing and glorious title of life. This therefore is promiſed in my text in oppoſition to that which we now lead to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the excellency and reality of that Heavenly Life, free from thoſe miſeries which now do attend us:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tolerantia tranſitoria Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rona aeterna, pugna modica merces immen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa, poena levis gloria inesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mabilis, dabo tibi poſt mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zem pro morte vitae aeterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem</hi> Aug. de civit. Dei.</note> As if our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour ſhould thus compare them together for the encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the faithful. What if my intereſt doth expoſe you to your enemies cruelty? what if you are forced to lay down your lives in the maintenance of my cauſe? what reaſon have you to prize ſo inconſiderable a loſs? when the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change</hi> brings unto you Returns of a more unſpeakable value. Grudg not to part with this ſhadow of life; Grieve not to ſurrender it: Refuſe it not when I ſhall require it: I have another life in reſerve for you, whoſe advantages do as high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly excel thoſe of this preſent being, as the Crown doth the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41499:8"/>other enjoyments of the body; a life both glorious and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Erit ſtatus omnium bono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum aggrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus.</hi> Boetius de conſol.</note> where nothing ſhall be wanting to increaſe your ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factions, but cares, trouble, and pain, which now do cauſe us to reliſh the ſweetneſs of our earthly pleaſures. <hi>I will give thee,</hi> &amp;c. This expreſſion preſents us with the greateſt vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of Excellencies. That they may better appear unto you, take a view of them, and of that ſupernatural eſtate of Heaven in theſe following propoſitions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It ſhall be an unſeparable union of the ſoul and body for all eternity. We ſhall live no more upon condition to die. The fear of death that doth uſually torment us more than the ſenſe, ſhall then ceaſe with the cauſe: Men ſhall never be diſquieted with thoſe importune Apprehenſions that diſturb us, as they did <hi>Belſhazzar</hi> in the midſt of his carouſing Cups, and that cauſe us to be weary of life as that Roman was, who being purſued by the cruelty of the Triumvirat, offered himſelf freely to his Enemies pleaſure to be delivered by death of the daily fear of dying.</p>
            <p>But then we ſhall be ſecure both from the ſenſe and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of death, and of all approaching evils; and we ſhall reſt in that bleſſed Tranquility that ſhall never have cauſe to dread an alteration; there ſhall be no more divorce made between the ſoul and body, it ſhall not be poſſible to ſeparate that moſt loving couple. Gods Wiſdom and Power ſhall joyn them together in ſuch a manner, that neither Time nor any Accident ſhall be able to cauſe a ſeparation. For God, upon whoſe pleaſure all his Creatures do depend, ſhall remove all deadly principles, and grant us an eternal conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance; which ſhall proceed not onely from his immutable Decree, and immediate influence, but alſo from the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and manner of the union of the two parties, that ſhall no longer be entertained by the aſſiſtance of the Creatures, and a ſupply from the Elements; but onely by a greater cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondency, by more ſpiritual and more ſutable Embraces. At preſent although the ſoul hath a natural tendency to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liven, to move and inform the body between them, there is
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:41499:9"/>a vaſt difference that can never conſent unto any conjunction without the mediation of the vital ſpirits extracted from the more ſubtil and purer ſubſtance of the meats refined by their ſucceſſive concoctions. But then our Bodies ſhall depoſe, and caſt off that groſs and earthly matter, and become more convenient companions of the ſoul by a nearer aſſimilation to that Celeſtial being; <hi>For this mortal muſt put on immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, and this corruptible muſt put on incorruption,</hi> as St. <hi>Paul</hi> teaches at large in the <hi>1 Cor. 15 Chap.</hi> where he further de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares the Myſtery of the Reſurrection, and of the eſtate of our bodies, in the 42, 43, 44. Verſes. <hi>The body is ſown in corruption, it is raiſed in incorruption; it is ſown in diſhonour, it is raiſed in glory; it is ſown in weakneſs, it is raiſed in power; it is ſown a natural body, it is raiſed a ſpiritual body.</hi> From hence we may diſcover the future ſubſtance of our Bodies, which ſhall be almoſt as ſubtil as thoſe earthly Spirits raiſed by the ordinary ſyſtole and diaſtole,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mercat. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>par.</hi> 4. <hi>claſ.</hi> 4. <hi>quaſt.</hi> 120.</note> the two motions of the heart, which Spirits have the neareſt acceſs to the ſoul of man, and by which it is tied to its preſent reſidence; for this bleſſed life and its eternity is eſtabliſhed upon a reſemblance and nearer relation between the ſoul and body, whoſe beings muſt be rendred more conformable before they can be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured from a diſſolution, or from the ſenſe of violence; becauſe that onely this conformity is able to render the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion unſeparable, and to free it by that means from the inſults and affronts of all enemies. It is therefore moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that it ſhall not be in the power of any beings to put us to the ſufferance of pain; for as the pain which proceeds from the body is derived from an apprehenſion or a poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of ſeparation from that being upon which it depends, or from that which tends unto it: As the pain of the ſoul doth from a ſeeming or a real ſeparation from God the fountain of all good, or from that which ſtands us in ſome manner inſtead of God: It cannot be imagined how they ſhall be able to ſuffer who are adorned with the qualities of immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, whoſe beings are free from alteration, and not ſubject
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:41499:9"/>to the leaſt weakneſs, and whoſe ſenſes ſhall never receive any contrary impreſſions, nor convey unto the appetite any evil apprehenſions: Our bodies ſhall be no more marked with wounds and ſcars, nor feel the effects of the enemies cruelty and malice. What a glorious advantage is this? we ſhall be armed againſt the aſſaults of all caſualties: we ſhall be ſecure from all attempts: we ſhall no more tremble at the ſight of a danger: neither corruption within, nor injuries from without ſhall be able to alter that perfect and happy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of our beings: In one word, nothing ſhall ever in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupt or diſturb us in the ſweet enjoyment of heavenly Bliſs; <hi>For God ſhall wipe away all tears from our eyes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 4.9.</note> 
               <hi>and there ſhall be no more death, neither ſorrow, nor crying, nor ſhall there be any more pain: for the former things ſhall be paſſed away:</hi> as is expreſly promiſed in <hi>Revel.</hi> 21.4. For that reaſon this glorious Eſtate is called a Reſt, becauſe it ſhall free us from all inconveniences that now do encreaſe our labours: it ſhall not conſiſt in a ſhameful ceſſation from all action, bur rather from thoſe troubleſome and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful operations, unto which our mortal condition do now condemn us. Therefore it was typified under the Law by <hi>Moſes</hi> Sabbath, in which none were to be employed in ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile work but were commanded to conſecrate that day in the ſervice of God: it was alſo ſignified by the ſtructure of the Tabernacle, in which ſome learned Rabbies do take notice, that Iron that is the emblem of War, affliction and trouble was not uſed, that being the viſible Type of this glorious Tabernacle of Heaven, where Gods preſence ſhall for ever dwell with his people: It intimates, that in this Immortal Sanctuary not made with hands,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>In gloria coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſti mira ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renitas perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta ſecuritas aeterna foelici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas.</hi> Bernard. ſup. cant. Serm. 2.12.</note> no Iron ſhall be mingled with the Gold and Jewels that enrich and adorn Gods Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace; no ſorrow, no ſickneſs, no diſturbance, nor diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ſhall ever come near us; but as a Father very well ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth himſelf: In Heaven there ſhall be a wonderful tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility, a perfect ſecurity, and an eternal felicity.</p>
            <p>So I paſs to the next advantage of this Heavenly life, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:41499:10"/>that is, A perfect Independency, and a freedom from the Creature; a freedom from all thoſe wants that do oblige us to crave aſſiſtance from inferiour beings; a freedom from the Elements, and their Authority, and from all obligations to mean ſubſiſtances; for this bleſſed life ſhall advance us to that perfection that we ſhall not ſtand in need of thoſe things that we do now enjoy; we ſhall be enabled with thoſe glorious qualities that ſhall make us be content in the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our ſelves; and when ſomething ſhould be wanting to the accompliſhment of our happineſs which we ſhall not poſſeſs in our ſelves, as we ſhall be promoted to the fruition of God; we ſhall there find it in him; we ſhall there meet with all that ſweetneſs and variety of Excellencies of which we ſee but the ſhadows in the Creature.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 36.8.</note> 
               <hi>There we ſhall be abundantly filled with the fatneſs of his houſe: And we ſhall drink out of the rivers of his pleaſures.</hi> It is impoſſible that any thing ſhould be ever wanting to them that ſhall be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to a perfect communion with God the Author and Creator of all things, to them who ſhall live under the daily expreſſions of his mercy and goodneſs: His Almighty Power inclinable to render them happy, ſhall continually ſupply and entertain them with immortal enjoyments, and furniſh them with thoſe things that are not to be expreſſed by the creature:
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.4.</note> The Greatneſs of Gods liberality doth make us conceive his Royal favours ſomewhat proportionable to his Infinite Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. <hi>Alexander</hi> could not give ſo little a ſumme to <hi>Pericles</hi> as 10 Talents: God will be no leſs noble to the Children of his boſome, to thoſe that he is obliged to raiſe to the higheſt felicity. But thoſe things that ſhall ſerve to encreaſe our ſatisfactions ſhall not be like thoſe that we now poſſeſs: they ſhall not put us to any expence to obtain them, nor to any trouble to preſerve them; they ſhall not weary and torment us as earthly riches do, nor oblige us to abaſe our ſelves; beſides they ſhall have this other advantage, they ſhall proceed immediately from God: It is far more pleaſant to drink of the Fountain, than to ſup of the ſtream; it is a
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:41499:10"/>greater ſatisfaction to behold the Sun, than to feel ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>direct reflections of the beams: O how pleaſant, and what an Angelical ſatisfaction will it be to continue for ever in the loving embraces of that gracious God from whom all good is derived? What advantage will it be that we ſhall there reliſh true pleaſures without the leaſt mixture of evil? for they ſhall immediately flow unto us from Gods Eſſence, from an eternal contemplation of his face, and an immediate enjoyment of his favour: we shall receive from Gods hand what he conveys unto us by other beings, and that in a greater abundance, and with far more ſatisfaction: for our bleſſngs are not ſo natural when they come from the fruitfulneſs of the Earth, and the influences of the Heavens, as when they proceed from a divine Bounty without any mediation. How ſweet therefore will our Heavenly comforts appear unto us, when God out of the tenderneſs of his Love shall freely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow them? when in this Celeſtial Court every one shall have an equal acceſs to the ſupream Authority, and depend onely upon God both for our ſubſiſtance, and for thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effable things that will contribute to our happineſs; A bleſſed Society, a glorious Abode, Holy and pleaſant Employs, the benefits of an eternal Peace, with ineſtimable Riches, shall be appurtenances of this Crown of life, but the ſatisfaction that will flow from thence, shall be ſwallowed up in that O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean of Joy which Gods immediate preſence and glory will create in our ſouls, that will become ſo many Heavens, where the inviſible Being will manifeſt himſelf in an extraordinary manner. Therefore St. <hi>John</hi> promiſeth,
<note place="margin">Rev. 21.3.</note> 
               <hi>God will dwell with us, and we ſhall be his people, and God himſelf ſhall be with us, and be our God.</hi> And elſewhere, <hi>He that overcometh ſhall inherit all things, and I will be his God, and he ſhall be my Son.</hi> Beſides I find this other advantage in an immediate ſupply of our wants from God, That we shall thereby be freed from that ſlavery that increaſes at preſent our diſcontents: It is no ſmall diſgrace to the Nobility of our Nature, that we should ſo impatiently purſue after, and ſo covetouſly embrace the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:41499:11"/>vanities of the world, and things meaner than our ſelves; it gives alſo no little occaſion of diſturbance to be obliged to labour after the poſſeſſion of that which can furnish us no real content, and that rewards our expectation and deſires with diſappointment. But then as we shall immediately re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive from Gods overflowing abundance, innumerable ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factions, we shall no longer diſcredit our ſelves by mean complacencies, and by the diſcovery of our natural weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and neceſſities; we shall no longer weary our ſelves in the purſuance of things unable to ſatisfie us with content: Upon God we shall depend, in his favour we shall be ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and by his happineſs we shall be happy; not as we are at preſent, for the happineſs of the world is increaſed as much by our wants, as by our enjoyments; but then as the conſtitution of our beings, and our eſtates shall be altered, we shall no longer know pleaſure and felicity by their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traries: in God we shall meet with the true and genuine taſte of all Excellencies without the leaſt mixture of evill. Unto this glorious dependency upon God, which St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſtyles,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.21.</note> 
               <hi>A freedom from the bondage of corruption, and the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of the Saints.</hi> God labours at preſent to bring and train us up, by weaning our affections from the world, and by inſpiring nobler deſires, that are not to be concerned for the poſſeſſions of this life.
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 7.30.</note> It is the drift of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Exhortation, who wills us <hi>To be indifferent in the uſe of the creatures, and not to abuſe our ſelves, or them by any fond Embraces, or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient wiſhes for that which is to ſubſiſt but for a moment.</hi> It is the concern of us all that aſpire to this independency, not to fix our hearts, nor our happineſs upon the world, but to be always ready to part with that which is but an impediment to our perfection and felicity; for that reaſon God exerciſes us with wants and afflictions, and prepares us for a Crown, as <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedo</hi> did <hi>Alexander</hi> his ſon, by actions and employments ſuitable to the Majeſty that we are one day to repreſent, and to the Excellency of that eſtate unto which we ſhall be promoted.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:41499:11"/>
            <p n="3">3. This glorious dependency upon God, that shall free us from all dependency upon the creature, shall proceed from an inward and perfect communion and unſpeakable u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with this ſupream Being; we shall be united unto him by our affections; Gods love shall be no more clouded with judgments and trials; it shall shine upon us without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terruption; our love in requital shall return him continual expreſſions of thankfulneſs; our deſires shall reſt in his ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency: all the motions of our ſoul shall tend to his Glory: We shall alſo be united unto God as the members are uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto the Head, by an inward and continual infuſion of his divine Spirit in our ſouls, and by an humble ſubmiſſion to the motions of divine Wiſdom that shall govern us; or as the ſubjects are one with their Prince, ſo God shall be one with us;
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.2.</note> he shall reaſſume the ſupream Authority which he exerciſeth at preſent by a Mediator, and shall appear as our ſoveraign Lord, whoſe glory will be our intereſt; we shall alſo be united unto God by ſuch a manner as is not to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed.
<note place="margin">Joh. 17.24. <hi>Admirald de vita aeterna.</hi>
               </note> Such will be this union as shall promote us to an inward ſight of God, to a perfect reſemblance with him, and to an eternal familiarity with God the Father; ſuch will be this union, that we shall enjoy with the Incomprehenſible Being the ſame felicity,
<note place="margin">Rev. 21.9.</note> and be ſwallowed up in the immen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of his glory, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.11. This union is ſignified unto us by a marriage, becauſe Chriſt conſidered there not only as a Mediator, but as God, shall enter into a ſtricter alliance with men, and shall become one with them in an unſpeakable manner. Therefore St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſtyles it a great myſtery.
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.32.</note> At preſent we are united unto God by the Holy Ghoſt, that is called the Spirit of Chriſt, by the reception of his benefits in the Sacraments, and by Prayer that cauſeth a continual enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe and correſpondency to be entertained between God and our ſouls: But then theſe imperfect unions shall ceaſe, and give place to a more perfect and glorious,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 3.19.</note> to a limited participation of all the divine Attributes that are communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable, to ſuch a union, as shall raiſe us above all natural capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:41499:12"/>our divine Eſtate unto which God deſigns us! By the preſent we may judge of the future:
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Vide coloſ.</hi> 1. 19. <hi>de Chriſto.</hi>
               </note> What means our graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous God to beſtow that coſt, to employ thoſe glorious Agents in our preſent ſatisfaction, if he intended not to bring us to a condition ſuitable to theſe hopeful beginnings? What means the Father to ſacrifice his onely begotten Son, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe him to all the affronts that nature is able to receive? What means he to ſend the Holy Spirit to enrich us with his moſt precious and divine Graces? Is it onely to reſtore our natures to their Primitive Integrity, that needed not the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currency of ſuch a Saviour, nor the expreſſions of ſo great a Love? or is it onely to fit us for an entrance into the Angeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Hierarchies? I hey would not have been ſo inquiſitive into that eſtate which they would have then underſtood; and the Sacred Trinity had never been employed in ſuch a manner in mans Redemption, nor had never honoured him with thoſe unſpeakable teſtimonies of divine love, if God had not intended him for an eſtate near unto himſelf. The holy Angels had never been miniſtring Spirits unto us, unleſs we had been the adopted ſons of God, and unleſs there had been ſomething in us that is to be worthy of their ſervices and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours which God deſigns for his eternal enjoyment: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is it alſo that our nature is advanced to an Hypoſtatical union with the divine Word? is it onely to enable Chriſt for the office of a Mediator? or is it not alſo to declare un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to what honour God would promote the reſt of mankind, were they as he is, free from error and vice? Wherefore do we labour to bring our lives and affections to a conformity with Chriſt, but that we that are his brethren might enjoy in ſome meaſure that advantage which he poſſeſſeth before us, and be united unto God, if not in the ſame unſeparable manner, yet in ſuch as may have ſome relation with that; wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs Chriſts Words in his Prayer to God at the eve of his Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
<note place="margin">John 7.21, 22, 23.</note> 
               <hi>I pray for them that they all may be one, as thou Father art in me, and I in thee, that they alſo may be one in us. And the glory which thou gaveſt me I have given them, that they may
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:41499:12"/>be one even as we are one, I in them, and thou in me, that they may be made perfect in one.</hi> Unity is the perfection, as well as foundation of number; all things have a natural tendency to it in the world: Therefore the Church of Chriſt of ſeveral Nations, being called to a participation of the rules of his goodneſs;
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.28.</note> they muſt firſt as the Rivers that run into the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean unite with God the ocean of all good, before they can come to the enjoyment of thoſe endleſs joyes and pleaſures that are onely there to be found. Other Reaſons and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages of Scripture may be alledged for this Truth, which makes St. <hi>Paul</hi> fly out into an Admiration, and St. <hi>John</hi> breathe forth nothing but wiſhes; all the holy Martyrs em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace and hug the Flames that did convey them into this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate. Was it not ſufficient, O bleſſed God, that thou ſhouldeſt deliver man from his deſerved puniſhment? was it not ſufficient that thou ſhouldeſt render him capable of thy favours? But muſt ſuch a favour be granted? muſt thou ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit him to a participation of the divine Nature by this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable Union?
<note place="margin">St. <hi>Peter.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>O the depth of the riches both of the wiſdom and goodneſs of our God!</hi> You know not mortal men what God hath reſerved for them that fear him! What may we not expect from his love when we ſhall come to this eſtate? If there be any good at Gods diſpoſal, any ſweetneſs, any pleaſure and benefit in heaven or in earth, it ſhall be theirs, and in their poſſeſſion,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.32.</note> unto whom he hath at preſent given his Son and Spirit, and will alſo give himſelf, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us.</p>
            <p>Beſides, this Union ſhall cauſe an interrupted Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion between God and our ſouls. God ſhall pour his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings upon us in abundance, and we ſhall render unto him unfeigned teſtimonies of thankfulneſs; We ſhall ſpend Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in his praiſes, and he ſhall ſpend his Treaſuries upon us; we ſhall think of nothing but how to glorifie him, and he ſhall ſtrive to ſatisfie us: we ſhall contend in mutual offices of Love and Friendſhip. O happy contention! O bleſſed communion! unto which our preſent Piety and Religion
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:41499:13"/>intends to bring us. We have now a communion with God in holy duties, and by his divine Spirit, for no other end but that we might thereby be prepared for his eternal communion in Heaven.</p>
            <p>In this Union and Communion with God, conſiſts the chief happineſs of the creature; for beſides that they ſhall remove from us whatſoever looks like an evil, they ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure unto us advantages ſuitable unto that ſupernatural ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and eſtate,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 64.4.</note> 
               <hi>Which eye hath not ſeen,</hi> &amp;c. Our preſent knowledge ſhall be changed into ſight; our hope into fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ition; our love to God into endleſs tranſports; our deſires ſhall be ſatisfied, our Prayers granted and turned into eternal Allelujahs; our underſtandings ſhall be no more darkened with ignorance; our wills no more corrupted with vice; a bleſſed perfection ſhall reign within us: And this ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from an immediate infuſion of divine Knowledge, and a communication of ſpiritual qualities; that ſhall fit us for the viſion of God, for we ſhall ſee his Face, and his Name ſhall be in our foreheads.
<note place="margin">Revel. 22.</note> 
               <hi>We know,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>John, when God ſhall appear, we ſhall be like him:</hi> For we shall ſee him as he is; not only with our corporal eyes we may ſee that inaceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible light which always accompanies the viſible declaration of his Glory and Power; but alſo with the eyes of our ſouls we shall behold as much of the eſſence of God as the creature can perceive he will expoſe himſelf to our view: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we shall be transformed into his reſemblance; we shall be as ſo many Images of the Godhead, ſo many living Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures of his Infinite Being, repreſenting his glorious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections as a clear fountain doth the body of the Sun, or rather as <hi>Moſes</hi> face did the brightneſs of the beams with which the Divine Majeſty was cloathed upon the Mount <hi>Sina;</hi> God will imprint in us the noble Characters and lineaments of his Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence: therefore well might <hi>David</hi> promiſe to himſelf, <hi>As for me, I will behold thy face in righteouſneſs, I ſhall be ſatisfied when I awake with thy likeneſs.</hi> So that this bleſſed life shall not ſo much conſiſt in the union of the ſoul and body, as
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:41499:13"/>in the union of both ſoul and body with God our Creator.</p>
            <p>In the next place, in this life there ſhall be an excellent order and ſubordination in our ſouls; all the paſſions and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections ſhall be ruled by the command of our Reaſon: Theſe inward motions shall not ceaſe, but they ſhall be bound to their good behaviour; they ſhall no more offer to raiſe a rebellion within us to diſturb our tranquility; they ſhall not be capable of evil impreſſions,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 32.18.</note> nor bear the marks of corrupted nature: There shall be a beautiful ſymmetry between the parts of our ſoul and body, inſomuch that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and integrity shall appear within and without. How happy shall that life be when we shall perfectly enjoy our ſelves! when all our affections shall endeavour to accomplish our felicity! Theſe are our preſent enemies; they procure all the inconveniences that happen unto us, whether in our bodies or eſtates, by perſwading us to embrace that ſeeming good, which proves our deadly poyſon. But then they shall be no more corrupted by the ſight of apparant advantages, nor tempted to betray our intereſt for a vain enjoyment: they shall always carry us to the performance of Duty, and to that real good which shall fully ſatisfie us with content. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they be thus reformed, it is not poſſible for man to taſte happineſs in the moſt bleſſed Eſtate: For what are Honours, Riches, and the greateſt Bleſſings, to one tormented with the deſire of an increaſe, or to a peevish diſcontented ſoul that apprehends a change, or ſees a happineſs afar off which it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers to the preſent, or to one whoſe paſſions gaul him: The leaſt pain is ſufficient to qualifie the greateſt pleaſures: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in this happy life unruly paſſions shall ceaſe with out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward inconveniences: they shall ſuffer us to relish the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our poſſeſsions; they shall rather awaken our ſenſes, and give them a fuller and a quicker apprehenſion of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of the heavenly delights: and although our happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs shall not be confined to thoſe pleaſures that are furnished by our ſenſes, for they are not ſufficient inlets to receive as much as the ſoul requires to accomplish her felicity; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:41499:14"/>it is not proper that the Bliſs of ſo excellent a part should depend upon its correſpondency with the baſer, or that it should borrow its ſatisfaction from its union with the body;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Caro ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alis effectae per omnes ſenſus ſuos multimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis exuberabit delitiis.</hi> Laur.</note> yet it is moſt certain, that they shall not want a share of thoſe pleaſures in which the ſoul shall ſo freely ſwim; they shall not be brutish, or ſuch as <hi>Mahomet</hi> promiſeth to his Mufulmans, but they shall be ſutable unto the ſpiritual body of the Righteous, and far excelling the baſe and rotten plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of this miſerable life, in quality, for they shall be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt mixture of bitterneſs in the quantity; for they shall be proportion'd to our capacities, and in the durance; for they shall be continual without interruption, and eternal, as <hi>David</hi> informs us,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 16.11.</note> ſpeaking unto God. <hi>In thy preſence is fulneſs of joy, and at thy right hand are pleaſures for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. This life shall be a life of Holineſs and Righteouſneſs; a life of Piety and Juſtice, and of ſobriety, a life of integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; for then we shall be arrived to the ſupreme degree of perfection, as well as of happines; we shall come to that perfect ſtature of regeneration which is in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord: The works of the Devil shall then be utterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, and that great diſorder which his Apoſtacy hath cauſed shall then be reformed. In Heaven no impure thing shall enter,
<note place="margin">Rev. 21. Heb. 12.14.</note> 
               <hi>For without holineſs none ſhall ſee God.</hi> The glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified shall never be able to offend their God, for the inward motions of the ſoul being rightly diſpoſed, according to his Will, and our affections perfectly reformed, the outward actions of the body muſt needs be conformable. When there should be another Serpent to tempt us, and another <hi>Eve</hi> to aſsiſt him, they could never prevail upon us, becauſe we shall be no more in a poſsibility of ſinning, for our under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings shall be no more capable of miſtakes, nor our wills corrupted with importune deſires, nor our actions forced from us againſt our election; And beſides this bleſſed diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition from whence shall proceed a conſtant practice of the Commandments of God, he will alſo by his continual in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:41499:14"/>to ſtrengthen our reſolutions, and determine our wills, that they shall abhor whatever might diſpleaſe him; the ſight of his holineſs shall convey the ſame diſpoſition into our minds, as St. <hi>John</hi> tells us: and his infinite power shall be engaged <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eſerve them whom his love hath eſpouſed, and for whom he hath been at ſo vaſt an expence to raiſe them to that eſtate; Therefore God we shall for ever adore with all the powers of the ſoul and body; his ſervice we shall attend with delight, our brethren we shall love without diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimulation. How pleaſant will this life be when there shall be a continual Emulation between God and his creatures, and between themſelves, who shall exceed in love and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? when all the glorified in Heaven shall interchange daily expreſsions of kindneſs; when there shall be a perfect agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, a living correſpondency, a ſweet fellowship, a delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful converſation, without envy or malice, without care or tediouſneſs. This is ſufficient to render us moſt happy, when all other things should be wanting, for happineſs conſiſts ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a perfect diſpoſition of the mind, than in a plentiful enjoyment of outward advantages. But beſides, our bodies shall be adorned with heavenly qualities; the preſent shall ſee a moſt happy change with the viſible ſubſtance,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Conveniens eſt us ſicut damnati ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent extremas tenebras ita beati habeant extremam lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem.</hi> Baſil. lib. Hexa. <hi>Caro ſine moln &amp; pondera ſine deformita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te ita ut ſit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimae orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum non tormentum</hi> Aug. Serm. 139. <hi>de tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>por. c.</hi> 3.</note> and other qualities ſhall be added with which we are not at preſent ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted: It is therefore needleſs to queſtion whether we ſhall know one another, ſeeing we ſhall ſcarce know our ſelves, the change will be ſo great: It is certain that we ſhall move without trouble, we ſhall aſcend without help; our ſtrength ſhall be encreaſed; our deformities removed; our infirmities depoſed; our appearance ſhall be full of majeſty and glory: as <hi>Daniel</hi> informs us; <hi>They that be wiſe ſhall ſhine as the brightneſs of the firmament, and they that turn many to righteouſneſs as the ſtars for ever and ever,</hi> In which words you may further obſerve a difference in the glories of Heaven ſutable to their inclinations and employments on earth; for the one ſhall ſhine as the Firmament, the other as the Stars: a ſenſible diſtinction ſhall be both in the nature, and the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:41499:15"/>greatneſs of their Rewards; for according to the ſeveral diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions of men, and their ſeveral capacities; God will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly beſtow upon them his riches, and his glory: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Father adviſeth us to enlarge our perfections, and the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of the ſoul by a continual exerciſe in humane ſciences, that they may be then more capable to receive and contain the myſteries of Gods Wiſdom, and better able to bring forth glorious actions for this eternal Sabbath is an eſtate where all our abilities ſhall be in the higheſt perfection; where we ſhall act and move without the leaſt inconveniency: Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions we may have to exerciſe our Vertues, not ſuch as will cauſe us to ſuffer, but ſuch as without that ſtrength of nature we ſhould find a default in our happineſs. It is therefore our wiſdom now to accuſtom our ſelves to that which ſhall be our employment for ever, and upon which ſhall depend our ſatisfaction and glory; which ſhall be revealed in us, as St.
<note place="margin">Rom. 18.18.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> informs us; <hi>In our ſouls by a perfect enjoyment of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernatural excellencies; in our bodies, that ſhall be free from all weakneſs, and beautified with glorious qualities.</hi> Therefore this eſtate is called a Crown of Life; for as the Crown is of a round and a perfect figure, it is moſt proper to expreſs the infiniteneſs and perfection of thoſe heavenly delights that shall accompany that life: beſides, the Crown is the ſacred emblem of joy and honour; this expreſſion therefore pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents us with the notion of the moſt pleaſant, and the moſt honourable eſtate together; for there is nothing more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable than life, nor more glorious than a Crown: and that we may better underſtand wherefore Chriſt promiſeth Heaven under this notion, we muſt take notice that chiefly four ſorts of perſons were dignified with a Crown amongſt the Ancients: Kings to expreſs their Authority and ſupream Command: A new married couple at the nuptial Feaſts therefore by the Greeks they were called <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The Prieſt in the ſolemn Sacrifices, to render the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering more acceptable, and the devotion more glorious, or rather to shew what qualification was anciently required
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:41499:15"/>in one that preſented to the Divinity the Homages of the people; Another ſort were crowned, they who had given open teſtimony of their valour and cunning, either in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Diſputes, and Plays allowed by authority, or in a publick War, in the maintenance of the general intereſt: To theſe ſeveral ſorts of Crowns were given, which were in value and eſteem according to the nature of the vertuous action. Now the faithful in Heaven shall be Kings, enjoying a ſupream command over the infernal Spirits and damned Souls. <hi>They ſhall be Prieſts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 2.26.</note> 
               <hi>ſending up unto God the perfume of their praiſes,</hi> They shall be married unto Chriſt in love and affection. In theſe ſeveral reſpects this Crown may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come them. But our Saviour in this promiſe hath more eſpecially an eye to the Crowns that were the rewards of a generous Perſeverance; that had obtained the Victory; for he mentions the difficulties that were to be overcome; A death to be endured; and adds this encouragement, <hi>I will give thee O faithful ſoul, a Crown of Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was the ancient cuſtom to crown the Temples of the dead Bodies when their lives had been exemplary:
<note place="margin">Plin.</note> by this ceremony the Heathens did expreſs a Reward that was due to a vertuous life, and the Honour which a righteous Soul hath purchaſed to himſelf: What they performed to the Body, Chriſt promiſeth to do unto both Soul and Body: <hi>I will give thee,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>You have ſeen the Picture of this Crown with many Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of the greater bulk; an infinite number of the leſſer ſort of Pearls and Flowers we shall never know but by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience: And ſo I proceed to a brief conſideration of the Aſſurance that my Text gives of this Eſtate unto the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful: <hi>I will give thee,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>It is no wonder to ſee <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate a profeſſed ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of Chriſt, a promoter of Gentiliſm, upbraid Chriſtians with the eaſineſs of their belief, and ſcoff at this perſwaſion, <hi>That there is a Crown of Glory to reward the Righteous.</hi> It is no marvel if amongſt the Heathens, men nurſed up with pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judices
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:41499:16"/>againſt the Truth, ignorant of the power and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our God, should call in queſtion the Articles of the Reſurrection of the dead, and of the happineſs of another life; but that in the boſom of Chriſtianity, under the moſt viſible expreſſions of Gods Omnipotency, Juſtice and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; there should be ſome of that dull apprehenſion as not to underſtand, and of thoſe ſtrange principles, as to oppoſe theſe ſacred and beneficial Truths, it may ſeem at firſt very ſtrange. But ſee what manner of men are capable of this folly amongſt us, and you will ceaſe from admiring; they are the Diſciples of <hi>Diagoras</hi> and <hi>Epicurus</hi> rather than of Chriſt, men that are degenerated into beaſts by their conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcention to bruitish pleaſures, whoſe ſouls are ſunk into their ſenſes, and have loſt both the uſe and knowledge of the nobleſt functions; they are thoſe that defie Heaven by their crimes, whoſe lives are a ſcandal, and their perſons a reproach to the ſociety: And do you wonder wherefore they are ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to theſe truths, that are no friends to the peaceable en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of their luſts, that lay before their eyes the punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that are reſerved for them? do you wonder if theſe graceleſs wits cannot comprehend an eſtate ſo far above their capacities, and contrary to the preſent: let their natural abilities be never ſo great; ſuch know no other life but that of the ſenſes, no other felicity but the carnal, nor other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights but of the body;
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.14.</note> and how is it poſſible that ſuch should have the leaſt apprehenſion of that ſupernatural condition that ſhall raiſe man and all his faculties to the higheſt perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of activity. It is a myſtery but onely to them whoſe minds are inlightned by the Spirit of God; they alſo have no clear inſight into this eſtate: Therefore Chriſt in my Text pities the weakneſs of our capacities, and adds to his promiſe of heavens glories ſufficient reaſons to convince us of the reality of theſe Rewards: They are contained in theſe Particulars. 1. In the Qualities of the perſon that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth, and his engagement; 2. In the nature of the Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, or in that excellent relation between the eſtate of the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:41499:16"/>faithful on earth, and that in Heaven: other reaſons ſhall be added, drawn from the rules obſerved in the diſpoſition of the Creatures. The perſon that promiſeth this Crown of Life, is deſcribed in the 8th verſe of this Chapter; <hi>The firſt and the laſt, which was dead, and is alive.</hi> By which words is intimated his ſufficiency for the performance: for thereby are ſignified his Divinity and Humanity, his death, by which he purchaſed this celeſtial Diadem for us; his Almighty Power, and his Truth, that are engaged to ſee us in the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Chriſts Death hath given us an unqueſtionable Right to this Crown, and to all its dependencies: Before in the eſtate of Innocency we had a natural claim to Heaven,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>In coelumque redire animas coelum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nire.</hi> Manil. lib. 4.</note> by reaſon of our ſoul that is an immaterial ſubſtance conformable to the celeſtial Beings: ſo that by this law of Nature eſtabliſhed in the Creation, which aſſignes unto every thing a final reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence where firſt it had its derivation: if man had continued in his integrity, he had always continued in that glorious Right, and might have called for an entrance into that Seat of Glory and happineſs: But this natural Priviledge hath been forfeited by Rebellion. The ſoul by ſin hath loſt together the Title to demand, and the Power to deſerve an admiſſion; and hath ſeen it ſelf baniſhed out of Heaven by the procure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of its two great adverſaries Guilt and Corruption. But Chriſt by his death hath overcome them, and all impediments; by his Blood he hath ſatisfied an offended Juſtice,
<note place="margin">Heb. 9.12, 14</note> and <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained for us an eternal redemption.</hi> Therefore he is ſaid to be <hi>a propitiation for us, and our peace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 3.25. Eph. 2.</note> 
               <hi>by whom we have an acceſs to the Father.</hi> And in 10 <hi>Heb.</hi> 19, 20. St. <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth, <hi>We have boldneſs to enter in to the Holieſt by the blood of Jeſus, by a new and living way, which he hath conſecrated for us through the vail,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>his fleſh.</hi> But the Infinite merits of our Redeemer have not onely re-eſtabliſhed us in our former Right, but purchaſed for us a degree of Perfection and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug. lib.</hi> 12. <hi>de Civit.</hi>
               </note> far above that unto which we might have aſcended by the ſtrength of Nature in the eſtate of Innocency, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:41499:17"/>to the judgement of the Fathers, and of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who in <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. therefore mentions many advantages which we have received by Chriſt, for one loſt by <hi>Adam,</hi> and tells us, that the blood of the former is far more effectual and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial unto us than the tranſgreſſion of the latter hath been hurtful: So that by this means, Gods eternal Juſtice is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged to bring us to this eſtate which hath been lawfully pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed for us:
<note place="margin">Heb. 9.24.</note> In order thereunto <hi>Chriſt hath tranſported our nature, and introduced it into the higheſt heavens, that it might take poſſeſſion in our names of Immortality and Bliſs.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 2.6.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. But the goodneſs of our Title to Heaven, into which Chriſt is entred, had not been ſufficient to ſecure us the fruiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, unleſs he had been enabled with a power ſutable to ſo great an undertaking: therefore we are informed, <hi>That all power is given to him in heaven and in earth. That God hath put all things under his feet; That he ſits at the right hand of God with the Scepter of an Almighty power in his hand.</hi> This is ſignified in the former deſcription, by being <hi>alive from the dead,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1.4.</note> an infallible teſtimony of the Divinity of our Saviour. As many difficulties, I confeſs, will ſtrive to hinder our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into Heaven, as there were nations that did oppoſe the Iſraelites paſſage into the promiſed Land; our ſelves and Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions are not the leaſt. But what cannot he overcome, by whom all things were created in Heaven and in Earth, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible and inviſible,
<note place="margin">Dan. 4.35.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c. who doth according to his will in the Army of Heaven, and amongſt the Inhabitants of the Earth, and none can ſtay his hand, or ſay unto him what dost thou.</hi> What difficulties will be able to fruſtrate his deſign, unto whom the Elements, the dumb Creatures, the Devils, and all things do yield obedience, who hath conquered Death in its own Territories; who hath an Infinite Wiſdom, as well as Power, to bring to paſs his intentions: So that what Chriſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth, he is fully able to perform.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Chriſt is Truth it ſelf; he is not ſubject to change, nor able to deceive us: He is not as <hi>Xerxes</hi> was, he crowned his Steerſ man in the morning, and beheaded him in the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:41499:17"/>evening. He is not thus unconſtant in his Affections and Promiſes. <hi>The heaven and the earth ſhall paſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 5.</note> 
               <hi>but one jot of his word ſhall not paſs until all be fulfilled.</hi> Seeing therefore that he hath promiſed to beſtow this Crown of life upon every faithful ſoul, he will preſerve them here by his ſpirit, he will convey and guard them at their ſeparation from the Body, by the miniſtry of his Angels, and will at laſt receive them unto this glorious eſtate. Here are ſufficient ſecurities for this Immortal Reward; Gods almighty Power, his eternal Juſtice, his Infinite Goodneſs and Love, and his unchangeable Truth, are all engaged to ſee the faithful crowned with Glory; ſo that it is as impoſſible that they ſhould fail of their expectation, as it is impoſſible that God ſhould deny himſelf. St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Perſwaſion, <hi>Jobs</hi> Confidence, and the Aſſurance of the holy men, were grounded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this infallible foundation. Were we poſſeſſed with the ſame ſpirit, we ſhould not need to ſeek for any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther confirmation of this Truth than the authority of Scripture, that often repeats the promiſe of this Crown unto the faithful. But this ſenſual age will ſcarce do God that juſtice, to give credit to his Word, as if he could have a deſign to deceive us, whoſe glory is our happineſs and perfection; as if he were an enemy to our good, who gives us whatever we enjoy; as if there were dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to expect the Rewards of Honeſty and Vertue, and to yield obedience when both Duty and Intereſt do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire it: Conſider the folly of our Modern Witts; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary advantages are promiſed unto men to oblige them to actions full of honour and ſatisfaction, when there ſhould be no ſuch future advantages; it is their preſent concern to entertain this perſwaſion, becauſe it is a friend to Piety, and it tends to ſtrengthen their reſolutions, to appeaſe their diſcontents, and to fill our ſouls with a glorious expectation: As that <hi>Athenian,</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:41499:18"/>that in his greateſt poverty, did feel the contentments of the wealthieſt Citizens; Men ſhould labour to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort themſelves in their preſent miſeries, with the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of a more bleſſed eſtate, and ſuffer their hopes to fruſtrate the deſign of worldly misfortunes. It ſeems therefore ſtrange, that Rational Beings ſhould be ſo great enemies of their good, as to diſcredit this bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial perſwaſion, and willingly to deprive themſelves of an Antidote able to fortifie their ſouls againſt the venom of evil. The excellency of that eſtate, the vileneſs of ours, and our natural unworthineſs, may juſtly fill us with wonder and admiration. But we are not to que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion this Truth, when not onely Scipture but Reaſon alſo is able to convince us that it is certain, according to the natural courſe of things, that he that is faithful unto Chriſt, muſt needs attain unto the greateſt happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. I underſtand the word <hi>faithful</hi> in the largeſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception for a <hi>vertuous man;</hi> faithful in the management of the ſeveral intereſts with which God hath intruſted him; for one whoſe life and profeſſion is conformable to Chriſtianity; who labours to reduce his Paſſions to reaſon; his deſires to content, his wants to ſufficiency, and that endeavours to ſtrengthen himſelf with all the natural and revealed perſwaſions that are intended to aſſiſt our Vertue againſt the inconveniencies that aſſault us. Such a one hath a degree of happineſs begun in him, and if he continues, exerciſe will bring him to that perfect diſpoſition of the mind, and to that noble temper as may brave all the attempts of evil. The <hi>Stoicks,</hi> by the ſtrength of nature, did attain unto a ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inſenſibility, witneſs the reſolution of <hi>Poſſidonius,</hi> in the midſt of the tortures of the Gout, he could never be forced to confeſs it to be a pain: witneſs <hi>Anaximan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> pounded in a morter, he laughed at the folly and cruelty of the Tyrant. How much more power ſhall
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:41499:18"/>man have over himſelf, when his reſolution is backt by ſuch ſtrong perſwaſions as Chriſtianity teaches, when ſuch divine helps do aſſiſt him, as the graces of the holy Ghoſt, an invincible hope, and a well-grounded faith, that makes him rejoyce in tribulation. It is therefore plain, that he that practiſes the Rules of Chriſtianity, muſt needs be happy, not onely in regard of himſelf, that he renders thereby capable of happineſs, but alſo in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of thoſe with whom we have a communication, that are invited by an amiable correſpondency, and good offices to the ſame returns and behaviour; and in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of God, who cannot but vouchſafe his bleſſings and his favour to that Being that is inſpired with ſo noble an ambition, and that in obedience to his holy Laws labours to arrive to perfection and holineſs. But beſides this reaſon which onely proves a natural hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs attainable by a vertuous Chriſtian in this life, we may meet with others in that great proportion or rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion between the eſtates of the faithful on earth and of the Saints in heaven. Caſt your eyes upon both, and tell me, what hinders a ſoul waſhed in the blood of Chriſt, adopted amongſt the ſons of God, united unto him by his divine Spirit; what hinders a ſoul full of heavenly affections, a ſoul that bears the Image of God, from an immediate fruition of his preſence and favour? If therefore that be granted that may be proved by the experience of the faithful as well as by the authority of Scripture; that they do really enjoy a preſent corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondency with their Creator, and that they do not in vain flatter themſelves with the conceits of an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary poſſeſſion, of the graces of the divine Spirit, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they feel the inward operation of this ſpirit in their ſouls,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Unius Sp. Sancti opus eſt regeneratio.</hi> Ambroſ. de Sacr.</note> and ſee a notable change in their diſpoſitions and affections wrought in them by his power alone, that faſhions us in the womb; if this be granted with the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:41499:19"/>other priviledges of the Elect, we ſhall find no difficulty to believe the happy conſequences that do naturally flow from thence; that God that favours them with ſuch powerful helps, in order to their perfection, muſt needs deſign them for a greater happineſs than their preſent mortality and weakneſs are capable of: That he would never be at ſuch vaſt expence and care as to provide us with ſuch divine qualities onely for this tranſitory Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, were our ſouls to be ſmother'd in our graves; that this bleſſed change that appears in our ſouls and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and that raiſes us to a capacity of being happy, and to a reſemblance with God, tends to prepare us for a more worthy communion with him; and that otherwiſe he would never have honoured us with ſuch ſpecial tokens of his Love, nor given us by them an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of greater advantages. This proceeding were not conſiſtent with the Wiſdom, Power, Goodneſs, Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racity and Immutability of God, to receive us into his intimate acquaintance, to beſtow upon us the unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able mercies that are ſuitable to it to make us expect future happineſs, and the eternal fruition of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence in Glory, and then to ſuffer us to be cut off by death without hopes of life; ſo that beſides that the condition of the Elect on Earth, and their preſent ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication have a neceſſary tendency to glorification, God would never have undertaken to render us happy, did he not really reſolve to make us ſo.</p>
            <p>But ſet aſide theſe conſiderations, and look upon a true Chriſtian as he appears to the eyes of the world: You ſhall find his deſcription given by a Heathen Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher to a Roman Emperour to this purpoſe; He deſpiſes the World and all its enjoyments, he ſticks cloſe to his Profeſſion, maugre all his enemies; he rejoyces in Wants and Perſecutions, and ſings merrily in the flames; his ſoul is full of hopes, and they ſtrengthen him againſt
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:41499:19"/>all preſent evils. What is therefore able to diſturb the happineſs of ſuch a ſoul that is raviſhed with its own enjoyments, and that contemns now all things elſe?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Justi afflictio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem requiem putant.</hi> Lact. lib. 8. mor.</note> what hinders the ſame power that hath freed the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full from the ſlavery of ſin and the world, and made us able to contemn the miſeries of our preſent condition, to free alſo the body from all ſubjection to the Elements? When therefore I ſee a Chriſtian ſo far advanced in the Race of Perfection as to leave in a little time the reſt of the world at ſuch a vaſt diſtance behind, I muſt needs conclude that he will make a conſiderable progreſs if he continues his courſe: Or when I behold a Painter chalk out to the life a fair face, I do eaſily judge that his pencil will be able to add many graces, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat it. Thus when I ſee the firſt Eſſayes of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian to be ſo glorious in this life, I am forced to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that the end of his work will be far more in the other. If <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas,</hi> in their Chains, can ſing for joy; St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſleep ſecure with pleaſure at the Eve of the day intended for his Execution, and all the holy men meet with happineſs and content in the moſt ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Penury, and the ſharpeſt Afflictions; How much more happy and content ſhall they be in that Life, that ſhall not be ſubject to want, to diſgrace and inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niency; in that Life where all things ſhall be as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and glorious as themſelves; when therefore Chriſt ſhould never have promiſed this eſtate unto the faithful, he that is ſenſible of their preſent condition, and of the honour and perfection unto which they have been advanced, he may juſtly conceive that they will arrive to an eſtate ſuitable to theſe promiſing beginnings. In the next place, if we caſt an eye upon the natural or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which is obſerved in the diſpoſition of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, we ſhall find ſufficient Reaſons to be perſwaded of this Truth.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:41499:20"/>
            <p>All the Beings in the world do generally attain unto thoſe Ends unto which their Creation did deſign them. And ſhall man only be excepted? Shall not he arrive to his glorious end, to happineſs? for which he was cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated, as may appear by his endeavours and deſires to obtain it, and by the conſtitution of his Being? Shall not he attain unto this eſtate when the union of the ſoul and body ſeems to promiſe it to him, in caſe he renders not himſelf incapable of it? Shall not he come to the fruition of God in whom onely his happineſs dwells? Is it poſſible that the power and wiſdom that appears ſo wonderfull in his compoſition, and that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares a particular eſteem of him by an over-ruling Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, ſhould onely deſign him for a world of miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and then tumble him in the duſt, without any further care of this Maſter-piece of the Creation? Or is it poſſible, that God ſhould ſuffer ſuch a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable ſpecies of Creatures to be caſt away for ever, and to miſs of their bleſſed End, and none of them to attain unto felicity, unto which it appears that he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended them at their Creation, by granting unto them noble faculties, capable of Bliſs?</p>
            <p>We ſee that all viſible things were made with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to turn to the benefit of ſome Beings more Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. And for whom was Man created? The more he excels the reſt in Perfections, the more honourable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit we may juſtly have for him for whoſe Glory he came into the world: And from the nature of man, and the place of honour that he maintains amongſt the Creatures, we may conclude, that this Prince of the lower World was created onely for the enjoyment of the Prince of the ſuperiour, and that he unto whom all viſible things do render Homage, owes his Reſpects and Being only unto the Creator. Our nature therefore deſigns us for the immediate fruition of God, and thoſe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:41499:20"/>inward ſuggeſtions that perſwade us to make our fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent addreſſes unto him, eſpecially at the ſight of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent dangers, do proceed from this deſign, and do tend as well to prepare us for a more immediate cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondency, as to ſupply our preſent neceſſities: And how is it poſſible to be advanced to that honour with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a diſpoſition, and without inward and outward qualities ſutable to that eſtate. From hence we may confirm the promiſe of this Crown of Life, and ſhew how every part is conſiſtent with the condition of a glorified Creature, and abſolutely required for the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of our happineſs.</p>
            <p>Examine alſo, I beſeech you, wherefore Man onely of all creatures enjoyes a being between the ſpiritual and the ſenſitive? wherefore doth he participate of both? Not that he might fall down to a greater conformity with Beaſts, for that is againſt the order of Nature, that teaches all things to aſpire to perfection, but rather that he might endeavour to aſcend to a higher degree; for no other intent man was made with a poſsibility of elevation, with capacious faculties, and with noble and aſpiring affections, but that they might raiſe him above that rank in which he was firſt placed and nearer his Creator.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Beatitudo in excelſo eſt ſed volenti peno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trabilis.</hi> Sen. Epiſt. 65.</note> Therefore mankind was intended for a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and a happy End; whoever employs all his endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to attain unto it, can never miſs of his purpoſe; and if ſo many do never come to that perfect Eſtate, they may thank their unworthy behaviour, and vicious diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition. But Chriſt that promiſeth this Crown unto the faithful, removes the grand impediments of Salvation, Guilt and Corruption, and brings them to that eſtate. So that beſides the helps of nature, they only have an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Power, and an Infinite goodneſs for their aſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants.</p>
            <p>We may therefore conclude from the former reaſons,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:41499:21"/>That there is ſuch an Eſtate as happineſs: That man was deſigned for it: that it is poſsible for him to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive unto it: that whoever is faithful to Chriſt, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to follow the rules preſcribed by him, muſt needs according to the natural courſe of things become hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, which cannot be in a perfect manner, but by an union and communion with his God. That this happineſs is not attainable in this life, I need not ſpend my labours in vain to prove, therefore it muſt be in another.</p>
            <p>Now this Crown is called a Gift: <hi>I will give thee,</hi> &amp;c. It is freely beſtowed notwithſtanding our undeſervings; it is recovered for us by the blood of Chriſt, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched with more precious Jewels, becauſe of his Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite merits; and the means by which we are raiſed to this Eſtate, is procured unto us by our Saviours ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and Aſcenſion. So that what Nature had intended, and was not able to perform, becauſe of our Apoſtacy and revolt from a dependency upon God, grace doth fully accompliſh in the faithful.</p>
            <p>In the laſt place, I might bring to confirm this truth the common Reaſons upon which the Heathens did build the hopes of a future happineſs, and of another life: Of the Juſtice of God, that will render unto every one according to his deeds: Of the Goodneſs of God, that cannot be forgetfull of thoſe that mind the advance of his Glory on Earth; and of the Power of God, able to reward them that lead a juſt and a religious life. From hence <hi>Zoroaſtes,</hi> that learned Genius and great Prince taught his Diſciples, That the chief care of man ſhould be ſo to behave himſelf now, that he might come to happineſs hereafter: Many other reaſons may be brought to confirm this important truth, but I cannot include them all in ſo narrow a compaſs as a Sermon. Some, I know, ſtumble at the difficulties of the Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of our bodies, when it is proved to them by
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:41499:21"/>their experience that it is poſsible:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Si ergo potent eſt Deus facere quod non fuit nonne poteſt reparare quod fuit?</hi> Aug. lib. de catech. Serm. 1. <hi>Secret dont oncomprent que quoy que le corps meure. Les formes font pourtant aux cendres leur demeure.</hi>
               </note> Conſider I beſeech you, if a leſſer power be not required, to reſtore what was than to create, or to make what was not: Where was this world before its Creation? and if that be doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, where was this age 200 years ago? not ſo much as in appearance, yet now it ſubſiſts. Why ſhall not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that ſame intelligent Being, who created the World, and who onely is able to have formed us in the womb, with all our members ſo well proportioned, be able to reſtore us to our ſubſiſtance again, ſeeing there is as great a diſpoſition in the eſſential parts of the body re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to aſhes, to return to their former ſhapes, as there is in the original ſubſtance to dilate it ſelf, and form the ſeveral members of a man. I might here al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the natural experiments which ſome have tried with ſucceſs: That have given occaſion to believe, that the forms of things do remain in their aſhes: The herb called by the Greeks
<note n="*" place="margin">It ſignifies not onely a Palm, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother herb mentioned by <hi>Dioſcor.</hi> lib. 4. cap. 151. and by <hi>Coel. Rodigin. Reſurrectio non eſt contra naturam.</hi> Aug. in Sent. ſuis.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> doth riſe again out of the duſt, when it hath been conſumed to aſhes: This cauſes the Fable of the <hi>Phaenix.</hi> I could alſo bring Nature and Providence to atteſt this truth; both are full of ſacred emblems of the Reſurrection: they are as incredible, did they not daily appear before our eyes. The faithful there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore may brave this and all other difficulties in the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of St. <hi>Paul, I am perſwaded that neither death nor life, &amp;c. ſhall be able to ſeparate us from the love of God, which is in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord. And henceforth is laid up for me a crown of righteouſneſs, which the Lord the righteous Judge ſhall give me at that day. I will give thee a crown,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Caſt your eyes Criſtians once more upon this Crown of Life; View the Bleſſedneſs; the Riches, the Glory and Honour of this Eſtate; and tell me whether this deſerves not our obedience, and a perſeverance in Duty: It ſhall be free from all weakneſs, pain, fear, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniency;
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:41499:22"/>it ſhall be accompanied with unſpeakble joyes and pleaſures; with the fruition of all good; with the Viſion of God, and with an eternal communion and union with him; It ſhall be adorned with all perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, holineſs and content. O rich and glorious Crown! O Immortal Reward! How long ſhall we be at ſuch a diſtance from thee? Earthly Crowns are troubleſome, and the more glorious they are, the more heavy; inſomuch that <hi>Diocleſian</hi> having exchanged one for a Spade, and the Empire for a Garden; when ſome were ſent to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade him to return to his former State, he told them they would never have undertaken that meſſage unto him, if they had but ſeen the Ranks of Trees, and the Musk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melons that he had planted, with the pleaſure that he did feel in that retired condition. But this Crown is of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther nature; the glories and honours are ſweetned with unſpeakable delights, and there is no ſuch wait as ſhould make us weary of the carriage: Let therefore this conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration encourage us to encounter Death without fear, ſeeing it is a paſſage into this immortal Bliſs, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare our ſelves for its enjoyment by a behaviour worthy of a Crown. Be faithful unto the intereſt of Chriſt, and his Religion; maintain his honour in the management of your ſeveral employes; follow his ſacred footſteps; ſhake off all vicious inclinations and cuſtoms: make it your buſineſs to reform your lives and affections; labour to reliſh the true pleaſures of the ſoul, and wean your ſelves from all worldly enjoyments, that they may not hinder your entrance into this eſtate. Into which God of his mercy receive us, for the ſake of his dear Son, and our Saviour, Chriſt Jeſus. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:41499:22"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
